JAIRO RUIZ SAENZ

Phone: (+57) 300 274 3441 – Bogotá, Colombia LinkedIn Profile: http://co.linkedin.com/in/jairoruizsaenz

Email: jairoruizsaenz@outlook.com GitHub: https://github.com/jairoruizsaenz

PROFILE

Bachelor of science in industrial engineering with experience in process improvement by providing technological solutions, with great analytical skills and high interest in areas such as information technology, front-end development, data visualization and data analysis.

EDUCATION

Universidad de los Andes, Bogotá, Colombia	Master of Information Engineering	October 2019
Universidad Sergio Arboleda, Bogotá, Colombia	Project Management Specialization course	August 2016
Universidad de los Andes, Bogotá, Colombia	Bachelor of Science in Industrial Engineering	February 2013

TOOLS

Python, HTML, CSS, JavaScript, Django, FastAPI, AWS, GitHub, Heroku, Tableau, Metabase, Microsoft Power BI, D3.js, Jupyter Notebooks, VBA, PostgreSQL and still learning more.

LANGUAGES

Spanish – Native English – Advanced - C1 | TOEFL 110/120 April 2022

COURSES

Data Science Training 2021

MinTIC – Correlation One (see credential)

September 2021

WORK EXPERIENCE

Docokids - Remote, Bogotá, Colombia.

Front-end developer. February 2022 – current

 I have been developing a new native website for the company, for this we are using Django as backend framework and HTML, JavaScript, CSS and Bootstrap for the frontend. I'm in charge of developing the frontend, however, due to my previous experiences I've also been able to develop some of the backend functionalities. You can check our website at https://docokids.com/

Departamento Nacional de Planeación, Bogotá, Colombia.

Data Scientist and Lead front-end developer – Digital Development Directorate. November 2019 – current

- I have provided support in the development of data analytics pilot initiatives to support decision making in public policy formulation. Participating in the development of projects involved in text analysis, descriptive analysis, implementation of machine learning models and others.
- I contributed to the development, release, and maintenance of the two open-source projects.
 - LEILA Data Quality Library (https://github.com/ucd-dnp/leila)
 - ConTexto Text Processing and Analysis Library (https://github.com/ucd-dnp/ConTexto)

Fondo de Pasivo Social de Ferrocarriles Nacional de Colombia, Bogotá, Colombia.

Data Analyst, Information Technology Consultant. August 2018 – December 2019

I worked in the development of an in-house invoice generator tool, I oversaw the data cleansing, implementation of
data processing scripts and database management. By the end of the project, I had developed a Django web
application for invoice generation and visualization, which allowed the company to significantly reduce the processing
time and within 6 months from the first prototype to generate invoices for more than 500.000 USD that had been
overdue for some time.

Universidad de los Andes, Bogotá, Colombia.

Teaching assistant at visual analytics class. September 2018 – December 2018

For more information visit the class's website
 http://johnguerra.co/classes/visual_analytics_fall_2018/ | https://cursos.virtual.uniandes.edu.co/isis4822/

Rappi, Bogotá, Colombia.

Business Intelligence Analyst – Algorithms Team. May 2018 – June 2018

• Provide support in data analysis, definition, and measurement of KPI related to the supply / demand balance.

Ministry of Information and Communications Technology. MinTIC, Bogotá, Colombia.

Data Analyst – Advisory Office of Planning and Sectoral Studies. August 2016 – May 2018

- Provide technical support in the process of implementation, development, and completion of the Pilot Project "Big
 Data for the measurement of the information society", in which the International Telecommunications Union ITU, the
 Ministry of Information Technologies MinTIC, the National Administrative Department of Statistics DANE and
 Comunicación Celular S.A. participated. CLARO.
 https://www.itu.int/en/ITU-D/Statistics/Pages/bigdata/default.aspx
- Provide conceptual and technical support for the preparation of sectoral studies, which served as input for public
 policy decision-making, such as the quarterly newsletter of the postal sector and the first major ICT survey.

South African Breweries - Miller. SABMILLER, Bogotá, Colombia. Business Transformation.

Data Analyst – Master Data. January 2015 – July 2015.

- Implemented processes required by the company in the Master Data Web Tool for different countries, such as Peru, Panama, and Colombia.
- Processes automation using connection between Master Data Web Tool, Microsoft Excel, and SAP software by using SAP scripting (VBA).
- Provided technical support to solve post go live issues on in-house master data web tool (MDWeb)

Financiera de Desarrollo Territorial S.A. – FINDETER S.A., Bogotá, Colombia, Administrative Services.

Analyst, May 2013 – July 2014.

- Participated in the Implementation of the insurance policies module of Microsoft Dynamics AX tool.
- Solved human resources issues related to travel allowances and reduce the lead time of travel allowances payments.
- Prepared the utilities expenses budget for 2014 fiscal year.

Cerro Matoso – BHP Billiton, Montelibano, Colombia, Mine / Maintenance Department.

Analyst, Internship. January 2011- July 2011.

- Implemented a VBA scripts I implemented a VBA script in Microsoft Excel to develop an inventory tracking file, which
 allowed the company to track the inventory of maintenance equipment and spare parts that were being manually
 tracked.
- Implemented VBA scripts for automation of data analysis report generation and KPI tracking.